Guide to the Madeline Lee Gilford Papers WAG.288
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Madeline Lee Gilford Papers
1940-2005
WAG.288
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
2.0 linear feet
Madeline Lee Gilford (1923-2008) was an actor, producer, and social activist who was blacklisted during the McCarthy Era and subpoenaed to testify before the House Committee on Un-American Activities (HUAC) in 1955. The collection contains correspondence, photographs, press clippings, programs, scripts, and speeches relating to her career and activism as well as documents pertaining to 170 Years of Show Business, an autobiography co-authored with actor Kate Mostel (1918-1986).
Gilford, Madeline
Historical/Biographical Note
Madeline Lee Gilford (1923–2008) was born Madeline Lederman on May 30, 1923 to Polish immigrant parents in the Bronx, New York. The youngest of four children, she began acting at the age of three at the Heckscher Foundation for Children’s Theatre in Manhattan segueing into radio, television, and film under the stage name Madeline Lee.
While a student at Walton High in the Bronx, Gilford joined the American Student Union. She continued to be active in progressive politics throughout her life and was a target of blacklisting during the McCarthy Era. In 1955 she and her husband, the actor and comedian Jack Gilford (1908-1990), were called to testify before the House Committee on Un-American Activities (HUAC) after being named by the choreographer Jerome Robbins. Madeline Gilford testified before the committee on August 17 of 1955. Gilford continued producing in television and theater under the assumed name of Maggie Giles including two early children’s television programs: the Attic Playshop and Sing A Song with Charity Bailey, the first interracial children’s television program in New York. Gilford co-authored an autobiography with Kate Mostel, which describes their lives in the entertainment industry and the effects of blacklisting on their careers and those of their husbands, Jack Gilford and Zero Mostel (1915-1977). The memoir was published in 1978 as 170 Years in Show Business.
Gilford had two sons, Joseph and Samuel, with Jack Gilford and a daughter, Lisa, from a previous marriage to Mitchell Fein, an engineer. Gilford died April 15, 2008 in Greenwich Village in New York City.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Lisa Gilford sent a gift of documents, books, articles, and photographs on areas ranging from blacklisting to the involvement of arts in political activism of accession in 2008. The accession number associated with this gift is 2008.040.
Gilford, Lisa; Grant, Lee, 1927-; Guthrie, Woody, 1912-1967.; Harburg, E. Y. (Edgar Yipsel), 1898-1981; Mostel, Zero, 1915-1977; National Committee to Reopen the Rosenberg Case.; Randolph, John, 1915-2004; Robeson, Paul, 1898-1976.; Blacklisting of entertainers.; Folk music.; Theater |x Political aspects.
- Series I: Subject Files, 1940-2005
  Scope and Content Note
  Series I contains correspondence, clippings, photographs, scripts, and speeches documenting Gilford’s career and social activism. A significant portion of the collection relates to 170 Years of Show Business. The series includes transcripts of Gilford’s testimony before HUAC and correspondence from the American Federation of Television and Radio Artists (AFTRA) regarding the failure or refusal of its members to answer questions posed by HUAC. Other notable items include correspondence from Woody Guthrie, E. Y. (Edgar Yipsel) Harburg, and Arthur Miller. Photographs include over forty scenes from Attic Playshop, a children’s television program produced by Gilford in the 1950s; publicity shots of Madeline Gilford, Jack Gilford, and John Randolph; the 1940 cast of Meet the People; and Robert Meeropol circa 1970s.
  - Appointment Calendar, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Blacklist: Clippings, 1961, 1980-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Blacklist: Correspondence, 1981-1995 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Blacklist: Programs, 1992-2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Casting, Apr 1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Center for Constitutional Rights: Docket, Fall 1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Children’s Television Programming: Attic Playshop, 1955, [1950s] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Children’s Television Programming: Sing A Song with Charity Bailey, 1953, 1954, [1950s] (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Clippings: General, 1955-1994, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Commission for the Tenth Anniversary of the Sandinista Revolution: International Symposium on Democracy and Revolution, 29037 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Congress Monthly, v. 53, no. 4, May-Jun 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: American Federation of Television and Radio Artists, Aug 10, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence: Arthur Miller, Apr 1940 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence: General, Apr 1940-Mar 2002, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence: Howard Linkoff to Federal Bureau of Investigation, Oct 1991 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence: John Randolph, May 14, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence: Woody Guthrie, Mar 1940, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cue, v. 46, no. 18, Sep 3-16, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Early Stages: City of New York Department of Cultural Affairs, May 1997 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Faulk, John Henry: Correspondence, Clippings, and Programs, 1988-1993, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Federal Works Agency, Work Projects Administration for the City of New York, Adult Education Program, Board of Education: Pamphlets, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Folk Music: Advertisements and Programs, 1952-1960, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Folk Music: Clippings, 1956-1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Folk Music: Ear to the Ground, Oct 1963, [1960s] (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Folk Music: “Folk-Say” Festival, Boston, 20486 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Gilford, Jack: Clippings, 1948, 1976-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Grant, Lee: Interview with Sylvia Drake, Oct 1990 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Harburg, E. Y. (Edgar Yipsel): Correspondence, Obituaries and Tributes, 1960s, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Headshots, [1980s] (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Hearings Before the Committee on Un-American Activities House of Representatives, Aug 15-18, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Institute for Media Analysis, Apr 1988 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Kazan, Elia: Correspondence and Clippings re Tributes, 1987-1999 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Look to the Rainbow: Clippings, Feb-Mar 1985 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Monocle, v. 6, no. 3, 23682 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Mostel, Zero: Clippings and Programs, 1977-1984, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - National Committee to Abolish the House Un-American Activities Committee: Correspondence and Pamphlet, HUAC: Bulwark of Segregation, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - National Committee to Reopen the Rosenberg Case, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - National Emergency Civil Liberties Committee: Bill of Rights Dinner: Correspondence, Programs, and Speeches, Dec 1992 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - National Emergency Civil Liberties Committee: Publications, 1960, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Obituaries, 1980-1998 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - 170 Years of Show Business: Advertising Mock-Ups, [1978] (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - 170 Years of Show Business: Clippings, Oct-Nov 1977 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - 170 Years of Show Business: Clippings, Jan-Aug 1978 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - 170 Years of Show Business: Clippings, Sep-Dec 1978 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - 170 Years of Show Business: Clippings, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - 170 Years of Show Business: Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - 170 Years of Show Business: Contracts, financial statement, schedules, 1976-1979 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - 170 Years of Show Business: Correspondence, 1976-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - 170 Years of Show Business: Drafts, [1970s] (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 170 Years of Show Business: Drafts, [1970s] (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 170 Years of Show Business: Drafts, [1970s] (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 170 Years of Show Business: Film Proposal, 1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 170 Years of Show Business: Photography Credits, [1970s] (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 170 Years of Show Business: Publicity, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Perelman, S. J. (Sidney Joseph): Clippings, 1974, 1979, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, 1940s-1980s (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Programs, 1965-2004 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Publicity: Personal, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Put Your Mouth Where Your Mouth Is: An Irish-Jewish Cookbook: Unpublished Manuscript Drafts and Clippings, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Races of Mankind: Ruth Benedict and Gene Weltfish, Public Affairs Pamphlet (85), New York: Public Affairs Committee Inc., 1943 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Robeson, Paul: Leaflet and Pamphlet for Paul Robeson Centennial Celebration; Clippings, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Rosenberg Era Art Project, 1985-1989 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Rosenberg Fund for Children, 1990-1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Rosenberg, Susan: Correspondence and Clippings re Imprisonment, 1987, 1989, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Scripts, 1962, 1964- 1965, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - World of Sholom Aleichem: Clippings, Correspondence, and Playbill, 1953, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Series II: Oversized, 1944-1988
  Series II contains clippings and programs relating to blacklisting in the entertainment industry, publicity for 170 Years of Show Business, and an annotated broadside commemorating the performances of Jack Gilford.
  - “The Blacklist Legacy: A New Generation in Hollywood Takes Political Sides Again, but Remembers the Red Witchhunt”, Judith Michaelson, Los Angeles Times: Clipping, 32068 (Box 3)
  - “The Blacklist Years: A Look Back to the Future”: Christy Macy, Forum, Winter 1987-1988: Clipping (Box 3)
  - Broadway Dissents: Week of the Angry Arts: Broadside, 1967 (Box 3)
  - “The Charter of the United Nations: Adopted in the City of San Francisco, June 26, 1945”, People’s Daily World, vol. 8, no. 151, section II: Clipping, 16617 (Box 3)
  - Gilford, Jack: Broadside, 1970s (Box 3)
  - 170 Years of Show Business: Broadsides, [1978] (Box 3)
  - “Their Greatest Picture”, Joseph North, People’s Daily World, vol. 11, no. 133, section II: Clipping, 17689 (Box 3)
  - The Worker, vol. IX, no. 32, 16290 (Box 3)